<template description="Console, Templates &amp; Commands" category="introduction"><line># The Console provides direct access to a running Act server.</line><line># Everything sent is a Python script which is executed by the</line><line># act server in a special context.</line><line></line><line># The following example is designed to walk through basic</line><line># operation.</line><line></line><line># To get started move the Template window to the side</line><line># and open up the Console window. Make sure you can</line><line># see both.</line><line></line><line># Every section of the template below marked with</line><line># #&gt;&gt; and #&lt;&lt; can be sent to the server.</line><line># To send only a specific region of a template, highlight</line><line># the region to send and press &quot;Send&quot;.</line><line># (An easy way to select entire lines is to move to the front of the</line><line># line, hold down shift, and press the down or up arrows).</line><line># If there is no selection, ALL data will be sent to the server.</line><line># Note: many of the supplied templates are designed</line><line># to be run at once. Using specific sections may not work</line><line># as expected.</line><line></line><line># Likewise, &quot;Use&quot; can be used to copy the data into the</line><line># Console command area where it can be modified and </line><line># sent later. Tip: The Console command area has a sent history.</line><line># This makes it useful for sending, testing and revising</line><line># commands.</line><line></line><line># First, let's say hello!</line><line># Highlight the line between #&gt;&gt; and #&lt;&lt; and press &quot;Send&quot;.</line><line># (Hint: place the cursor at the start of the line beginning with</line><line># &quot;print&quot;, hold down the shift key, and press the down arrow once.).</line><line># &gt;&gt;</line><line>print &quot;Hello world!&quot;</line><line># &lt;&lt;</line><line></line><line># In the output area of the Console, &quot;Hello world!&quot; should</line><line># be displayed. This brings us to the next topic--</line><line># how are results displayed?</line><line># There are two methods. The first is to use print as</line><line># demonstrated above. The second is to assign to the &quot;_&quot;</line><line># variable. Lets do some math:</line><line># &gt;&gt;</line><line>_ = (1 + 2) * 3</line><line># &lt;&lt;</line><line></line><line># The console should display &quot;9&quot;.</line><line></line><line># Both the 'print' and '_' may be used together, but results from</line><line># print are displayed in order an only the last value assigned</line><line># to _ is returned. Each result will start a new line.</line><line># &gt;&gt;</line><line>print &quot;The sky is&quot;</line><line>_ = &quot;orange&quot;</line><line>print &quot;is &quot;</line><line>_ = &quot;blue&quot;</line><line># &lt;&lt;</line><line></line><line># Take some time to play around with the Console and </line><line># Templates. Remember, you can execute any valid</line><line># Python code.</line></template>